hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today in springbot I
will tell you one more very important
annotation conditional on property so
this what makes this annotation very
important because in a large scale
application where there are thousands of
beans right and many of those beans are
initialized during application startup
okay so it will clutter your application
context during with the unnecessary
beans also which might you not required
so that's where this annotation comes
into the picture and that's what make it
very very important interview question
that how we can uncluttered our
application context with unnecessary
being okay so we will understand this
properly with an examples and advantage
and disadvantage of it so let's start so
what does it mean conditional on
property as the name says that being is
created conditionally what does it mean
if condition becomes true Bean would be
created if condition is false beans
would not be created okay so just
understand this understand with this
example you already know the behavior of
this so I have created two class no no
SQL connection and my SQL
connection both are annotated with at
theate component just a Constructor
inside it similarly I have DB connection
which has dependency on this my SQL
connection and no SQL connection okay
again at theate component uh managed by
Spring Boot and then we have at theate
post construct uh which only get
initialized only get invoked after the
bean is successfully created so there I
am printing that okay uh DB connection
be is created and if this object is null
or not if this object is null or not
okay so you know that if I start the
application what would happen so when I
to start an application what would
happen is by defaults are single turn so
means eagly initialized so what would
happen is no SQL connection object would
be initialized so it's initialization of
no SQL Bean initialization of my SQL
connection Bean will get
printed okay after that spring boot also
find this because this is also single
turn by default so after the bean is
created it will try to uh inject the my
SQL
and no SQL dependency into it so it will
inject it so this is the object for this
one and this is the object for this one
so after this post construct would get
invoked DB connection being created with
dependency below it will print is my SQL
object null no it will have the proper
object
reference
false is no SQL object null no false
okay so you already know the behavior of
of this but now if interviewer asks
you what if you want to create only one
being either my SQL or no
SQL okay so the background of this
question is that in a company what
generally happen
is there is a kind of a migration always
some migrations keep on happening so
let's say that company is migrating from
my SQL
to no SQL
now company has now let's say fully
migrated now they want to stop creating
Bean of
it only want to create a bean of this no
SQL so that's why the question can comes
here is if you want to create only one
bean either this or this depending upon
the migration some
feature so this is the use case
one and another use case which comes is
that we have two components sharing same
code base but one component need my SQL
connection and another need no SQL
connection so the background of this is
that in most of the application what
generally happen is let's say you have
two application
application
one application two and there is
some let's
say common code base
so this application in its pom.xml
file has
dependency on this common code base
similarly application two also has in
pom.xml
dependency is set for this common code
base so both the application is depend
on this common code base now in this
common code base you have my SQL
connection
and no SQL connection
class now no SQL connection class is
needed by application
one and my SQL connection is needed
by application
2 but the question is that for
application one my
SQL should not Bean should not be
created and for application 2 only my
SQL connection Bean is required no SQL
Bean should not be
created so in short the same same only
one bean can be created for an
application so how you can do that the
answer is atate conditional on property
annotation it's a very very simple but
important to understand the use cases
properly so now the same example I am
showcasing with at theate conditional on
property
annotation so here in this one here if
you see the same class my SQL connection
annotated with adate component and no
SQL connection class annotated with
atate component but now here I am adding
one more annotation at theate
conditional on property now this has
four parts one is
prefix second is value so these two
prefix and value forms your key in an
application do properties so in
application do
properties the first part is your
prefix then there is a DOT and after dot
whatever the part you have that makes
your value so here we have SQL
connection as a prefix enabled as value
so in application property your key
is uh SQL connection do unbled so this
is your
key okay
so this becomes
your key now with prefix and
value right separated by
dot now the third part is having value
so this is an string so here you can put
anything right so for now in this
example I have put SQL connection do
enable true you can also put any string
let's say SQL or anything right it's an
string so for now I have just put true
so now what it will do is the third part
is
match so in the application do
properties whatever the value you have
put here for this key whatever the key
value you have put here it will match it
with
this here okay so that's what I'm trying
to say this is just an string you can
put uh here if you are putting SQL you
can also put SQL here also so it's just
a matching
string so for this prefix do value which
makes a key in an application do
property whatever the key value it
is it will if it get match with this
having value this if it get match with
this then only Bean will get
created
okay if not if they are not
matched then Bean will not get
created okay so there is one another
thing is match if missing so let's say
in application. properties this uh this
key is not not present itself so do you
want to consider it as uh being I should
create Bean or not so that's all if you
make it false
means if this property is not present if
this key is not present considered as
false you should not create the
bean so you got this right this four
values of this
so now what do you understand with this
so here in the conditional on property
SQL connection do enabled in the
application do properties I have put
true having value is also true right uh
and match if missing is false similarly
for no SQL prefix is this no SQL
connection enabled having value is true
match if missing is
false okay so now
this is first
part this annotation is just a first
part and this is your second
part so wherever you are using
this dependency so now my DB connection
is dependent on my SQL and no SQL and
these classes are annotated with atate
condition on property so we have to make
this required equals to
false because when you only do
autowired by default internally your
required is
true okay by default required is true
what does this tells to the spring boot
that hey when you are creating a bean of
DB
connection object of if Auto is true
required is true the object of this
dependency should get resolved means it
should be present this object should be
present
but when you say that required equals to
false means that object might not get be
present means for this my SQL connection
I have put required equals to false so
it tells that hey conc is not as a fast
fail if if the bean you don't find the
bean of my SQL connection it's okay
required is false right make it null and
proceed
further okay so you understand right
required equals to false is
required is required whenever that
particular dependency let's say in this
case dependency is my SQL connection
here so that is annotated with at theate
condition on
property okay so these are the two parts
whenever you use at theate condition on
property now you start an application
what would happen so now when you start
an application so first spring boot will
see this okay at theate compon
uh it is a default is single turn so it
is eligible for lazy initial um not lazy
eager
initialization but now it it see hey at
theate conditional on property is also
defined so it will make a key using this
prefix and value SQL connection.
enabled it will make a key look into the
application. properties okay it found
the key now it will check out it value
key value it's true now it will compare
this string with this having value okay
now it matches if it matches means yes
object need to be created so this object
will get created initialization of my my
my SQL connection being so
initialization of my SQL connection be
now spring boot found this no SQL
connection it's a single turn yes uh
eagerly initialization can be done but
now at the rate condition on property
found it now it make a key no SQL do
unable no SQL connection do unable so
now it will look into the application do
property does it found this no SQL
connection do unable no so it match if
missing so it is missing I have to match
it false so means there is no match so
Bean should not be created for this one
so here if you see there is no Bean for
no SQL connection is created
now this got the springb got this again
a single turn eagerly initialization so
Bean would be created for DB connection
now it will resolve the dependency for
this
two my SQL Bean is existing yes my SQL
be is existing so it will get a
reference for this one
object no
SQL no SQL a being existed no because on
conditionally condition become false
right because this uh prefix value
doesn't exist so bean is not created so
bean is not created but it will check
hey the required is marked as false or
true so it is false then it's okay it
will keep it null but if it is marked as
true or by default you didn't give it uh
don't give it then it is considered a
true only in that case this will
fail right but since we have make
required equals to false means even
though Bean doesn't exist for this it's
okay it will make it null and proceed
further so DB connection Bean is
created post construct object is method
is invoke so it will print this line
first DB connection being
created is my SQL connection object null
this
one no because this be is created right
my SQL be is created because uh the
prefix value was present properly
so it's false first one is false no it
is not
null is no SQL object null yes it is
null because it's uh prefix value there
was no key present and that's why it uh
become false and No Object
created okay so it will PR true here so
you got it now I am controlling the
creation of a being through this
annotation
okay and it's configurable means you can
put into your application. properties
and if you want to uh enable no SQL
connection you can put here no
SQL
connection do
enabled I told you right it is just a
string you can put let's say you want
instead of true false you can put no SQL
something and the same value you can put
it here no SQL so means one this two
matches right this two matches this two
string matches then only it is
considered as this uh hit and then only
Bean would be created right and if
itself it is missing missing means you
can tell okay if it is missed I still I
want to create a bean put true if it is
missing and you don't want to create a
bean put
false okay so I hope this would be clear
so what are the advantage and
disadvantage of it very
important Advantage first is very very
visible is toggling of feature right I
told you right first use case in which
happens into the company is that they
keep on migration happening so you can
put a toggle now you want to toggle from
my SQL to no SQL using just in
application. property you can add this
toggling and automatically that
particular Bean will getting
created right avoid cluttering of
application context with with
unnecessary beans consider the scenario
where application of thousands of beans
out of the thousands of beans there
might be so many beans which are not
unnecessary right so we can avoid
application context to be like cluttered
with those unnecessary beans and we can
control them their creation using this
annotation save memory so during
application startup all the bean get
created and it is stored
so it requires certain
memory right so when you are controlling
the creation of the beans and you are
not creating Bean of the
unnecessary uh classes then you're
saving the memory right so that is also
one
advantage another is reduce application
startup times so I told you all eagerly
initialized being which are generally
single term at the when you start an
application that time object is created
for them being is created for them now
consider that during application startup
you have to create thousand beans right
so it will definitely take memory and
the time also so if you're controlling
that okay for Unnecessary beans I don't
have to create it your application
startup time will get
reduced okay so these are the advantages
we should uh we should tell when
interviewer ask and the disadvantage is
that misconfiguration can happen so for
example now in the application.
properties you have to put the value
right so misconfiguration means you
wanted to put true but by mistake you
put false you wanted some value SQL here
you have put SQL but somewhere here put
true having value true you want it true
false but somewhere put SQL so some
misconfiguration happens right code
complexity increases code complexity
increases when overused
now consider the scenario where you have
100 of classes and above 100 of classes
you have put this annotation now it's
always you have to go and check the
property file hey is this Bean creation
is what's uh is it enable or not right
so that is like little code complexity
increases where it's always like is will
the bean will get created or not you
have to keep on checking application.
property
file third is another uh is like
multiple Bean creation with same
configuration so what
if what if if the same
configuration with the SQL connection.
enable what for the no SQL also I am
using SQL connection. enabled what if
the with the same configuration I am
controlling the bean creation of
multiple classes that is wrong right
this creates confusion so multiple Bean
Creation with same configuration brings
confusion so that should be
avoided complexity in managing I already
told you you have to keep on managing
the property files and their value
equivalent values in this uh annotation
so there is some managing you have to do
so these are the advantage and
disadvantages of this annotation but do
try it out because this is used a lot in
the live application production
application right and and this is a very
valid two use cases which today in live
you will find this use cases and where
this U annotation helps you okay so if
you have any doubt let me know we can
discuss more and we'll see you in the
next video thank you bye